<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[codebar]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//"/>
  <updated>2015-12-14T22:28:11+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.codebar.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[codebar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EuRuKo 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/12/14/euruko-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T20:35:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/12/14/euruko-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Salzburg and the Sound of Music are traditionally inseparable, but there was little traditional about the sound of music in the Salzburg Congress hall in the middle of October.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/salzburg.jpeg" alt="Salzburg" /></a></p>

<p>Joseph Wilk (<a href="https://twitter.com/josephwilk">@josephwilk</a>) was one of the presenters at <a href="http://www.euruko2015.org/">EuRuKo 2015</a>. He gave a talk and demo turning Ruby coding skills into a live performance.</p>

<p>What’s new and exciting about making music from code, Joseph said, is that it doesn’t matter that he’s making code. He’s simply making music.</p>

<p>Getting away from the traditionalist view of coding as something exclusive for certain types of programmers, is very exciting for him about coding today.</p>

<p>&ldquo;We’re reaching a point where people are starting to not accept how they’re told to use code. People are starting to say: let me discover for myself how I want to use it.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;And that brings wonderful new things together in new ways, like weaving and coding and design and coding. People are starting to break apart the technology and designing for themselves from scratch.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Some of these new things are what Dot, from <a href="https://codebar.io/brighton">codebar Brighton</a>, liked best about the conference.</p>

<p>&ldquo;You come to get an in-depth understanding of what’s involved in some aspects of the code.&rdquo; she said. &ldquo;But also to get different ideas. I’d never thought to make a game in Ruby.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;It was interesting to see Ruby in the GUI since we often tend to think of Ruby as a language that is only useful for writing web backends.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;When you’re writing Ruby in the day-to-day work environment there are many things you don’t think about, the conference shows you some of the fun things going on and some of the more obscure things.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Those obscure things included <a href="http://64bites.com/">64bites.com</a> founder Michał Taszycki (<a href="https://twitter.com/mehowte">@mehowte</a>) show the audience how to program a Commodore 64 and Amy Wibowo (<a href="https://twitter.com/sailorhg">@sailorhg</a>) demonstrate an exploration of origami’s cut and fold problem.</p>

<p>People of all ages and from countries all over the world came together under the umbrella of a common language in Ruby.</p>

<p>A language that allows people to think up an idea, work out how things need to be, and then make it into a working prototype or even program.</p>

<p>Dot, Foirell, Kriszta, Jen, and Sally from our codebar communities in London and Brighton went to the conference thanks to amazing London sponsor, <a href="https://shutl.com/uk/">@shutl</a>!</p>

<p>The keynote speaker was none other than Yukihiro &lsquo;Matz&rsquo; Matsumoto, the chief designer and mastermind behind Ruby.</p>

<p>He kicked off the conference with a visionary look at the interesting new stuff that the Ruby Core team is planning to add to Ruby, told through the humour of a Japanese language lesson. To the attendees relief, he also promised compatibility with Ruby 2.0.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/matz.jpeg" alt="Yukihiro Matsumoto" /></a></p>

<p>Some of the more scientific and challenging talks were less Ruby specific: Bradley Grzesiak (<a href="https://twitter.com/listrophy">@listrophy</a>) spoke about simplifying challenging software problems with rocket science, while Satoshi Tagomori addressed a data analytics service and its Ruby usage.</p>

<p>Some combined both. Hanneli Tavante (<a href="https://twitter.com/hannelita">@hannelita</a>) spoke on Humanising Math and Physics on Computer Science. She said Ruby was her first language of choice because,</p>

<p>&ldquo;We see Ruby for DevOps such as automated scripts, or a simple parser, but it can fit most scenarios, and it&rsquo;s usage depends on what kind of performance you need and requirements.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;It’s easy for me to think in Ruby, but I think in Ruby and then if I need to for example, translate into Python. The syntax I find really pleasant too.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The language itself is very easy to write and it has some very interesting features. Ruby is good for beginners, and for senior developers.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;What’s new and exciting is also the development of the language towards new languages we have, such as Elixir, or Rust.&rdquo;</p>

<p>A more fun and personal highlight was the demo by Amy Wibowo – Fold, paper, scissors – an exploration of origami’s cut and fold problem.</p>

<p>The fold and cut theorem states that it is possible, given a piece of paper and any polygonal shape, to find a series of folds of that paper such that the given shape can be generated with a single cut.</p>

<p>Her talk explored a Ruby implementation of a solver that determined the correct series of folds given any input polygon.</p>

<p>What were some of the other take-aways?</p>

<p>René Föhring has created a tool called Inch, an inline documentation quality check, to get people excited about inline docs. <a href="http://shoesrb.com/">Shoes</a> for cross-platform GUI, <a href="http://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi</a> for music composition, RbNaCl for cryptography.</p>

<p>In addition to the learnings, the Ruby community clearly also had a great time together over two days, and at the spirited Saturday night after-party.</p>

<p>That spirit is one reason to join a conference but also to join a community or club all year round.</p>

<p>Lisa Passing, Tam Eastleigh and Sarah Regan formed the <a href="http://rubycorns.club/jekyll/">rubycorns</a> in Berlin in 2013, a project group for Ruby beginners to learn and work on an app together.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/rubycorns.jpeg" alt="rubycorns" /></a></p>

<p>&ldquo;One of the challenges of learning Ruby is keeping motivated, it’s hard to know how to do that as a beginner. The community is great. People are kind and welcoming and excited to teach me.&rdquo;</p>

<p>And if she was starting out, I asked Lisa. What would she start with?</p>

<p>&ldquo;Start with a project like an app that you love to use, and build a clone of it. For us it was creating a list of support groups. Then figure out what you want to do. Figuring that out might be for fun or it might be your way of earning a living.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Typically Ruby is not as popular as other languages. While there are Ruby jobs out there, there are many more PHP and Java jobs but to Kevin McPhillips, Developer Team Lead at <a href="https://www.shopify.co.uk/">shopify</a>, the language you use is less important than being excellent.</p>

<p>The event&rsquo;s key sponsor told the audience that the market is massive and that attendees had, for example, probably used a Shopify store but not seen it behind the scenes:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Our core application is written on Ruby on Rails but we have a huge technology stack. Java, Python for the data science team, Go for some of our more concurrent tools.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The company is hiring. We’re looking for people not specialists. I can teach someone a tool, we can teach excellent people anything.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Be excellent. As coders, as communicators, and as a community, that was a theme that hit all the right notes. Perhaps the best take away of all.</p>

<p>Check out the speakers’ decks here: <a href="http://eventifier.com/event/euruko2015/slides">http://eventifier.com/event/euruko2015/slides</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What makes a good beginner open source issue?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/11/20/what-makes-a-good-beginner-issue/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-20T18:44:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/11/20/what-makes-a-good-beginner-issue</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the days leading up to our 24 Pull Requests event, we asked the community to submit good, beginner-friendly issues they found on Github for our students to work on during the event. Our 24 Pull Requests themed event is a day of helping beginner coders get started in contributing to open source software. The most common question we got was what constitutes a good beginner open source issue? The question is valid, especially from the perspective of a seasoned developer who can make sense of very specific jargon and can understand other developers&#8217; intentions from a few brief sentences. That isn’t the case for a complete beginner. As someone who was once a beginner - some would say still is - I think I can give some tips on what kind of issues helped me get started with open source and what kind of issues might suit other beginners.</p>

<p><strong>Small bugs, or very small features</strong></p>

<p>As a beginner it is important to start with small, succinct tasks. Things that can be solved in a day or better, an hour. Remember, when you are a beginner, contributing to open source isn’t only about fixing the bug but everything else that comes with the process: forking the repo, cloning it, setting it up, finding the bug, fixing it, adding, committing, pushing, opening the PR and so on. This might mean relinquishing some control of your project and offering up quick fixes and small features to potential contributors. Yes, you might be able to fix that small bug in two seconds yourself and never think about it again, but for a beginner that two second bug might be the issue that sets them off on a journey of contributing to open source.</p>

<p><strong>Issues with a clear context</strong></p>

<p>We’ve all seen issues on Github with a non-descriptive title like ‘remove no-js tags with js’. No description, no context. This in principal sounds like something a beginner with very little Javascript knowledge could do. Right. Detect whether an element has a no-js class and consequently remove it. But the lack of context makes it almost impossible to understand what the actual issue is and what is expected of the contributor. A good beginner issue has a clear description and gives as much guidance as possible without actually solving the issue. You are a project maintainer and might have an idea where in the project the bug might lie? Good, include the partial you think the bug might be coming from. You have a visual representation of the issue? Great, include a screenshot of it. The more details you include the better.</p>

<p><strong>Projects with a setup guide</strong></p>

<p>Not once have I found an issue on Github I deemed solvable with my limited skills only to find out the project has no setup instructions. As I mentioned in the first point, setting up the project itself is one of the most daunting parts of starting to contribute to open source. I have personally abandoned several projects because I got stuck whilst setting up the local dev environment and found the effort of reaching out to the maintainer or figuring it out on my own too much compared to the relatively easy task of solving a simple issue. If you want people to contribute to your project please take the time to write clear and detailed setup instructions.</p>

<p><strong>Responsive project maintainers</strong></p>

<p>It can be extremely discouraging to finally open that first PR you’ve worked so hard on, to then not hear from the maintainer for weeks, sometimes even months. We at codebar are guilty of this too. It is hard to always be up to date on a project from a maintainers point of view, but it is extremely important for a beginner to get prompt feedback on their PR. Don’t be afraid to give feedback either. If you don’t like the design they did for example, or want them to refactor some code, let them know in a respectful and objective way. The key is clear and respectful communication and collaboration.</p>

<p><strong>It&rsquo;s not only about code</strong></p>

<p>This has been said many times but code is not the only way to contribute to an open source project. Think about all the other components that make up a project: documentation, visual design, UX, user testing, accessibility, etc. These are all components of your project that you can open up to the community. But don’t over do it either. I’ve seen many, many issues that simply stated &lsquo;write documentation for xy&rsquo;. How would a beginner, who relies on documentation more than anything, know where to start with it? Provide a rough draft of the documentation and ask people to contribute to that.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>All of this means that project maintainers have to put in the time to create issues that are clear and understandable. It means they have to aid and help out beginners to contribute to open source projects. This may mean holding someone’s hand in fixing their first issue and submitting their first PR on the project. Yes, this takes time and effort, but it’s the only way to build a community of willing participants around a project and to get more people involved in open source.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[uncodebar, a codebar unconference]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/10/18/uncodebar/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-18T19:44:35+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/10/18/uncodebar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here at codebar we run over a hundred workshops a year for people underrepresented in the tech industry - 52 in our Central London chapter alone. All this is possible thanks to our dedicated coaches who volunteer their free time to come and teach our students week after week. While codebar is all about the students, we wanted to acknowledge the hard work our coaches put into codebar to make it as successful as it is.</p>

<p>With this in mind we devised uncodebar, the codebar unconference. We wanted to run an event that focused on our coaches, a platform for them to come together and share knowledge with each other. We wanted this event to be an informal, casual space that encouraged collaboration between coaches and strengthened the already vibrant community we built in the two years of codebar&rsquo;s existence.</p>

<p>So on the 10th of October 2015 we all gathered in the <a href="https://gocardless.com/">GoCardless</a> offices in London for a day of talks and workshops, all given by our coaches. For those not familiar with the format, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference">unconference</a> is a participant driven event, a loosely structured conference emphasizing the informal exchange of information and ideas between participants. At an unconference, the schedule is open ended and is put together on the day by the participants, who fill in the spots with talks or workshops they have prepared for the event.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/uncodebar-schedule.png" alt="putting together the schedule for uncodebar" /></a></p>

<p>We were floored by the eagerness of the attendees to contribute to the event and by the kind way everyone treated each other. We had an amazing array of talks, with topics ranging from <a href="http://richardwestenra.com/d3-talk/#/">Data Visualization with D3.js</a>, Intro to Docker, <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/arkham/regexr4strn-3">Regular Expressions for the Strong of Heart</a>, <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1V5pJqTC68-dGH26xlkBVdz7uSX5atQXQ5TAnPHDr6Eo/edit#slide=id.p">BEM and SMACCS</a>, <a href="https://adz.co.de/talks/#the_brain_the_gut_and_your_job.html">Behavioral Economics for Developers</a> to Introduction to Property Based Testing in Haskell. We participated in a Failure Swapshop and had a fun <a href="https://github.com/shecodesbtn/lets-get-physical">Arduino session</a> making LED&rsquo;s blink. We had plenty of breaks where attendees could break out into smaller groups and get to know each other better. We had amazing food and plenty of beers to keep the conversation flowing. We finished the day with a quick round of lightning talks that included a groundbreaking talk on <a href="http://slides.com/deniseyu/taylor-swift">Taylor Swift Driven Development</a> by our very own <a href="https://twitter.com/deniseyu21">Denise</a>.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/uncodebar-arduino.png" alt="arduino workshop at uncodebar" /></a></p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/uncodebar-swapshop.png" alt="failure swapshop at uncodebar" /></a></p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/uncodebar-food.png" alt="food at uncodebar" /></a></p>

<p>We were exceedingly happy that the attendees had the same impression of the day as we did. We received nothing but positive feedback, this quite from <a href="https://twitter.com/ThisIsJoFrank">@ThisIsJoFrank</a> particularly explains well why we think the event was a succes:</p>

<blockquote><p>Every talk that I went to was interesting, engaging and well presented. The coaches are a talented lot, the wealth of information shared was proof of that, but it wasn’t just shared knowledge, it was the encouragement and enthusiasm that everyone brought to the day and the feeling of positivity and mutual respect that really made uncodebar stand out from other conferences that I’ve attended.</p></blockquote>

<p>Of course none of this could&rsquo;ve happened without the support of our sponsors. Thanks to <a href="http://www.8thlight.com/">8th Light</a>, <a href="http://codurance.com/">Codurance</a>, and <a href="http://www.crowdmix.me/">Crowdmix</a> for their generous donations and <a href="https://gocardless.com/">GoCardless</a> for hosting us in their offices.</p>

<p>All in all we had an amazing day filled with inspiring workshops, talks, conversation and good food. The event had a great energy and we walked away after the day feeling inspired to continue our work with codebar and thankful to be part of such an inspiring community of technologists.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/uncodebar-participants.png" alt="uncodebar participants" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bournemouth codebar]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/09/08/bournemouth-codebar/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-08T21:05:25+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/09/08/bournemouth-codebar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>codebar is a non-profit initiative that facilitates the growth of a diverse tech community. We run regular programming workshops for women, LGBTQ and people from underrepresented minority groups. Our goal is to enable our students to learn programming in a safe and collaborative environment and expand their career opportunities.</p>

<p>codebar sessions run for 2 hours, in which students can choose to follow either our set <a href="http://tutorials.codebar.io/">tutorials</a> or focus on a personal project. We take pride in offering a 2:1 student to coach ratio so students get the attention they deserve.</p>

<p>Predominantly our sessions run across the UK but more recently we have expanded to Brazil, America and now&hellip; Bournemouth!</p>

<p>Bournemouth has a vibrant tech scene which is growing rapidly - it has an estimated 450 creative agencies in the area and is home to the world&rsquo;s largest Open Device Lab. It is also host to over 100 events a year; including meet-ups, hack days, unconferences and full blown conferences. Oh, and did I mention that the beach was voted the best beach in the UK and fourth best in Europe:</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/bournemouth_beach.jpg" alt="Bournemouth beach" /></a></p>

<p>Now our request to you. codebar&rsquo;s mission is to teach programming but for this to happen we need your help. Yes you reading this blog post. We need your help spreading the codebar mission, help getting coaches on board and help getting people involved who want to learn to code. We also need sponsors, as without them codebar would not be possible. They provide us with space, food, drinks and of course internet. So, if you work somewhere that could host a codebar then please contact us, <a href="mailto:hello@codebar.io">hello@codebar.io</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/codebarBmth">@codebarBmth</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Get involved</strong></p>

<p>Our first workshop will be held on Tuesday 13th October at <a href="http://www.wearefolk.com/">Folk</a> from 6:30pm. If you want to attend this workshop as a coach or a student you must <a href="http://codebar.io/member/new">sign up via the website</a>, equally if you know someone who is interested in coding and fits our eligibilty criteria get them to sign up too. Or if you want to help us by becoming a host for this chapter then please email us at <a href="mailto:hello@codebar.io">hello@codebar.io</a>.</p>

<p>P.S Thank you <a href="https://twitter.com/mattnortham">Matt Northam</a> for the incredible picture of the beach.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing West London chapter]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/07/06/london-chapters/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-06T17:46:19+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/07/06/london-chapters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to your enthusiasm, codebar London has expanded rapidly in the past couple of months. I’m sure you have noticed the waiting list getting longer every week and the number of attendees per event rising steadily lately. Not only that, London is a massive city with students and coaches living scattered around it’s area, with some people having to travel up to an hour to attend certain workshops. This obviously is not an ideal situation as we want our workshops to be easily accessible by the most number of students, with a number of attendees at each workshop that is still manageable by us (the organisers) and is not a hindrance to learning (taking too long to organiser ourselves, etc&hellip;).</p>

<p>To combat this situation we have started running events in <a href="http://codebar.io/south-london">South London</a>, on top of the original <a href="http://codebar.io/london">Central London</a> location and now we are adding <a href="http://codebar.io/west-london">West London</a> to the roster. The Central and South London workshops will both be held on Wednesdays, while the West London workshop will be offered on Tuesdays. The first West London <a href="http://codebar.io/workshops/150">workshop</a> will be held on the 14th of July, 2015.</p>

<p>A quick note about the different London chapters: you are more than welcome to sign up to all three of them and attend whichever workshop is most convenient for you that week. But please do not double book yourself on workshops (especially in the case of the Central and South London workshops which run on the same day). We do not have time to go through names and remove you from a list. Please bare this in mind when confirming your attendance for a workshop. Please also be respectful of other students: if you can no longer attend a workshop cancel your attendance through the site so someone else can take your place. Hopefully the increased number of workshops will allow more of you to dip your toes into programming and take part in the codebar experience.</p>

<p>On another note we have been nominated for the Grassroots Event of the Year award at the <a href="https://thenetawards.com/">net awards</a>. This is an amazing achievement for us as it is nominated by you. So if you have a spare 10 seconds please <a href="https://thenetawards.com/vote/grassroots/codebar/">vote for us</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Responsive Day Out 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/06/26/responsive-day-out-3/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T10:23:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/06/26/responsive-day-out-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friday 19th June was a brilliant day, partly because of the glorious sunshine and partly because 12 codebar Brighton students spent the day at the 3rd and final Responsive Day Out ‘The Final Breakpoint’ thanks to ticket giveaways from the lovely people at <a href="http://clearleft.com/">Clearleft</a>.</p>

<p><strong>What is Responsive Day Out?</strong></p>

<p>Responsive Day Out is a day conference comprised of topics branching responsive web design. It gathers designers and developers sharing their workflow strategies, techniques, and experiences with responsive web design.</p>

<p><strong>What is Responsive Web Design?</strong></p>

<p>Responsive web design is the practice of building a website suitable to work on every device and every screen size, no matter how large or small, mobile or desktop.</p>

<p>Building responsive websites primarily requires the use of HTML, CSS and possibly Javascript skills. This resonated well with the codebar students that attended as they have been building on these skills at codebar. The codebar tutorials don’t yet progress onto building responsive sites so this really got everyone thinking about how they could extend their current skill sets to encompass these ideas. It was also a real eye opener in to just how much there is to think about when designing for cross browser and cross platform.</p>

<p><strong>The Day!</strong></p>

<p>The conference was held at the Brighton Dome Corn Exchange, anyone who has been to Brighton will know that this is a beautiful building, well located between lots of nice places to eat and drink. The staff were friendly and helpful and the breaks made for a great opportunity to get to know some of the other attendees.</p>

<p>There were 12 talks, all of which were engaging and of high quality. Talks were grouped in 3s (around 20 minutes each) followed by a quick chat between conference host Jeremy Keith and those speakers before breaks for sun and coffee.</p>

<p><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/codebar_rdo.jpg" alt="codebar group photo" /></p>

<p><strong>The Speakers</strong></p>

<p>As codebar is an event aimed at encouraging diversity in tech we were pleased that there were so many inspiring female speakers on the bill. To us it signifies women holding strong presence in this industry. It is encouraging for other women either starting out or further into careers, when it is actively projected that women should be present, seen, heard and their knowledge shared.</p>

<p>The audio recordings are already available on the <a href="http://responsiveconf.com/2015/">Responsive Day Out 3 Page</a> but here is a quick overview of a few of the talks:</p>

<p><strong>Alice Bartlett -</strong></p>

<p>Alice is a front end developer at GDS and her talk title was ‘What is the business case of accessibility?’ She opened the conference, creating a great atmosphere as her speaking style came across very confident and naturally funny. She spoke about the alpha and beta stages of the GDS site and the process of making the site accessible. Ideas were developed with an objective: Not to frame what people may lack but instead to design in terms of what they (GDS) should provide. Through her experiences and through writing this talk, Alice found that accessibility is not the easiest businesses case to make but morally we should never need a business case for it. She recommended quick ways to improve accessibility to a site are running a screen reader over it and adding Aria. She also recommended joining discussions on the GDS <a href="https://designpatterns.hackpad.com/">Hack Pad</a> where design ideas are shared.</p>

<p><strong>Rachel Shillcock -</strong></p>

<p>Rachel is self employed, often designing for entrepreneurs with a focus on female entrepreneurs. She spoke about accessibility and how it isn’t something that can be tagged on at the end - no body should be left behind. She shared useful tools for making a site more accessible which will be especially useful for codebar students looking to make improvements in that area. These tools included <a href="http://leaverou.github.io/contrast-ratio/">Contrast Ratio</a> an online colour contrast checker that gives an A, AA or AAA accessibility rating for a colour against a background colour. Another was <a href="http://khan.github.io/tota11y/">tota11y</a> which lets you add a checklist to your page which will rate and advise your pages’ accessibility. Plenty of advice can also be found on <a href="http://a11yproject.com/">a11yproject</a>. She concluded that ultimately testing on real life people will help you achieve the best results.</p>

<p><strong>Alla Kholmatova -</strong></p>

<p>Alla is an interaction designer at FutureLearn. She spoke about taking a modular approach to design. She had found that a lack of shared language had hindered the original design process. They focused on perfecting the language used when naming components. A key takeaway was about how it was much harder to design ‘a kit’ than it was to design a whole page but the results were worthwhile. Another interesting part of their design process was that they actually handed away control from solely the designers and involved team members across disciplines. When working with users they worked with paper cards displaying the components which gave a more tangible and creative experience.</p>

<p><strong>Jake Archibald -</strong></p>

<p>Jake spoke about Modern Progressive Enhancement. Jake began by talking about performance and how the part to focus on is the time between the 1st render and 1st interaction. He spoke about the frustration of ‘lie-fi’ aka when your phone is telling you that you are connected but in reality the page never loads. He introduced the <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/service-worker/introduction/">Service Worker API</a> and how this will open up possibilities to browse offline. He demonstrated an app that allowed the user to make Wikipedia pages available offline. The problem then occurred if the user wanted to click on a link from the offline page and were not connected. In this instance, Service Worker could ask if the user would like to be notified when the page is available to view and could then send a push notification when the user next become connected. This seems like it would be very useful… especially for train journeys.</p>

<p><strong>Ruth John -</strong></p>

<p>Ruth’s talk was brilliant as she had prepared lots of demonstrations for using different web APIs. These included the geolocations API, web animation API, web audio API, ambient light API and more. There is a Web Audio API book by Boris Smus available to read for free online which comes recommended. Hopefully this triggered a few project ideas for codebar students!</p>

<p><strong>Rosie Campbell -</strong></p>

<p>Rosie works as a Technologist at BBC Research and Development which we thought seemed like a very cool job to have. She spoke about a research project they had undertaken with smart electronic wallpaper. The idea is that this wallpaper covers the walls in your living room and then when you watch tv the wall paper can change to give more of an immersive viewing experience spilling beyond the boundaries of the TV. You could be watching Glastonbury and there could be festival maps or set times or maybe a ‘Blur’ wall if Blur were playing with artwork from the band, possibly a crowd wall too. If there was a build up to a TV show you liked, maybe the photo frames could be slowly filled with character images over the course of the build up. This seems would also be great for parties if music videos could be projected all around the room.</p>

<p>Rosie spoke about designing with constraints to breed creativity which is why they kept a TV in the design. We recommend you read more about the Unconventional Screens project <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/rd/projects/unconventional-screens">here.</a></p>

<p><strong>Lyza Danger Gardner -</strong></p>

<p>Lyza was great to watch, very engaging and brilliant at telling the her story. She spoke about the conflicts she felt around being a generalist and working as a software engineer.  When she discovered HTML in 1993 she felt huge excitement - that she could reach the world with some p tags on a page. She loved pursuits with tangible results and felt the web was a generalist paradise. The web took a big leap when CSS was introduced and over time she began to find the complexity of the web tiring.</p>

<p>Before the web, if you heard lyrics on the radio you couldn’t just google the song. You had to look up academic information in reference libraries, but now with the web we are the reference library. More and more new frameworks are released and it can lead to demotivation and feelings of incomplete mastery making it much harder to be a generalist.</p>

<p>Lyza mentioned that she loved the word ‘developer’ which is something that resonated with some of the codebar students, it is great to be able to develop and carry out ideas. She spoke about how it takes bravery to feel like a beginner again and again as changes happen in the web. It is comforting to know that everyone feels out of their depth at times when learning.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>Responsive Day Out was a fabulous experience and we are slightly sad that this was the last one! Thank you very much to Clearleft and all the speakers. We came a way with a lot to think about and plenty of ideas to incorporate into our own projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mind the Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/06/17/mind-the-code/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-17T22:17:50+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/06/17/mind-the-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Saturday 4th June we organised Mind the Code, a day dedicated to mindfulness. Our aim was to run a slightly different event to anything we have ever ran before, where the day consisted of talks, workshops and yoga.</p>

<p>The day began with a few lightning talks from all of our sponsors and the first main talk of the day by <a href="https://twitter.com/emilyatk">Emily Atkinson</a>, developer and product manager at <a href="http://uk.moo.com">Moo</a>. Emily’s talk focused on coding mindfully. The first half of her talk focused on viewing code as a means to solving a problem. She discussed that as a developer you do not sit down to ‘write code’, you sit down to solve a problem. The second half of her talk was trying to get the audience to think about how other people view your code, and compared this to the foundations of a house. You want a solid base so that other developers can jump into the project and build upon your code without ruining your previous work.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/MTC-EmilyAtkinson.jpg" alt="Mind the code - Emily Atkinson" /></a></p>

<p>The second part to the day was an exercise on domain modelling. Students and coaches were paired up randomly and asked to design a new system for managing the London Tube system. Using paper and pens, we asked them to think about the concepts behind this model, classes, and who would be responsible for these classes and the relationship between them.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/MTC-Exercise1.jpg" alt="Mind the Code - Exercise 1" /></a></p>

<p>Once the first half of the day was completed, the first Yoga session was taken by Sandrine. This was then followed by lunch, provided by <a href="http://pronto.co.uk">Pronto</a>.</p>

<p>Next began our main coding workshop. The task here was to pick one of our set <a href="https://github.com/deniseyu/mind-the-code/tree/master/projects">projects</a> and begin building it with their coaches. The projects included a yoga slot machine, yoga lullabies, yoga pose name generator, online mode ring and a to-do list. The aim of this workshop was to get the students started on a projects of their choice.</p>

<p>We then had a second yoga workshop, for those that did not do it the first time, followed by the afternoon session of lightning talks. The <a href="http://slides.com/kimberleycook/motivation#/">first lightning talk</a> was by <a href="https://twitter.com/kimberleycook91">Kimberley Cook</a>, codebar organiser and front-end/iOS developer at Pixeled Eggs, on motivation. The <a href="http://gylippus.github.io/lightening-hybrid/#/">second lightning talk</a> was by <a href="https://twitter.com/heryandotus">Ryan Hanna</a>, mobile developer at Sworkit, on building hybrid apps with HMTL/CSS and JS. And the <a href="http://slides.com/alexpeattie/love#/">final talk</a> was by <a href="https://twitter.com/alexpeattie">Alex Peattie</a>, CTO at Peg, on developing mindful code regardless of your level.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/MTC-lightning-talk.jpg" alt="Mind the Code - Alex Peattie" /></a></p>

<p>After the lightning talks we had the second part to the coding workshop, which was a continuation of the first workshop. We stressed that the projects did not need to be finished as the workshop was more about what it means to develop software, and to have fun building it too.</p>

<p>We want to say a huge thanks to all of our sponsors <a href="http://mailjet.com">MailJet</a>, <a href="http://shutl.com/uk">Shutl</a>, <a href="https://www.twilio.com">Twilio</a> and <a href="http://beta.makersacademy.com">Makers Academy</a>. Also a huge thank you to <a href="https://twitter.com/MintSugar">Michela Tannoia</a> for designing our stickers. Without all of your support the day would not have been possible. And a final big thank you to all the students and coaches who attended and made our first Mind the Code an absolute blast.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Clojurebridge London]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/05/05/clojurebridge/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T23:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/05/05/clojurebridge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On Saturday April 18, Kriszta, Jarkyn, and Denise took part in London&rsquo;s first-ever <a href="www.clojurebridge.org">Clojurebridge</a> workshop, hosted at uSwitch&rsquo;s sunny offices in Southwark. We learned TONS of Clojure &ndash; our brains were mush by the end of the day! &ndash; and were able to experience how a workshop can successfully cater for many different experience levels. The students participating in the workshop came from all different backgrounds. Some were full-time developers looking to pick up some functional programming as a hobby; others were newcomers to coding altogether.</p>

<p>As newcomers to functional programming, we quickly realized that we would need to think about problem-solving in a completely different way if we were to become good Clojure developers. Unlike object-oriented languages such as Ruby or Javascript (most of the time..), functions are first-class citizens in Clojure &ndash; quite literally, because the function precedes each list. Because objects don&rsquo;t exist in the same way as Ruby objects, they can&rsquo;t hold state. As a result, data passed into a Clojure function is processed in a consistent, predictable way. Clojure can also developed with fast feedback cycles because it is richly supported by instant REPLs in several editors. An interesting side effect of this is that, while Test Driven Development (TDD) has many evangelists in Ruby and Java communities, TDD did not seem to have the same following in the Clojure community.</p>

<p>We worked our way through the Clojurebridge tutorials relatively quickly, then spent lots of time experimenting with our new skills. We wired together a basic web API and practiced making requests to some public APIs, which is where Clojure really steps up to bat. I was sold on Clojure when I saw how elegantly and efficiently you can traverse an HTTP response.</p>

<p>But, a blog post on Clojurebridge would be incomplete without a shoutout to the amount of hospitality we received! The organisers, sponsors, and hosts made sure there was no chance of us going hungry at any point. A constant stream of bagels, fruit, cheese, sandwiches, coffee, tea, and beer kept us caffeinated and energized. Codebar has to step up our game now&hellip; :)</p>

<p>For anyone interested in learning Clojure, there are a wealth of resources online. Here are a small handful of them:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://clojurebridge.github.io/curriculum/#/">Clojurebridge Tutorials</a></li>
<li><a href="http://clojurekoans.com/">Clojure Koans</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.4clojure.com/">4Clojure</a></li>
<li><a href="http://learn-clojure.com/">Learn Clojure</a></li>
</ul>


<p>For information on Clojurebridge London and their upcoming events, check out their <a href="http://www.clojurebridge.org/#events">official website</a>. There is also a vibrant community of <a href="http://www.londonclojurians.org/">London Clojurians</a> who hold weekly meetups in various formats.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[South London codebar]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/04/19/south-london-codebar/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-19T12:13:48+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/04/19/south-london-codebar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last Wednesday saw 24 students and 12 coaches attend the first ever South London Codebar at <a href="https://www.pactcoffee.com">Pact Coffee HQ</a>. The structure of the event was the same as normal, a lightning talk followed by a 2 hour workshop, this time just south of the River Thames.</p>

<p>The lightning talk was given by Tony To, tech lead at Pact Coffee, about&hellip; you guessed it Pact Coffee. He gave us an insight into what life is like at Pact and the journey the coffee goes through, from delivery to their HQ to distribution to customers. He also gave us a little introduction into the tech that Pact Coffee use to maintain their website and app, and how a Raspberry Pi powers their distribution printer.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/tony-sl-talk.jpg" alt="Tony To" /></a></p>

<p>Then as normal students and coaches were matched up for the 2 hour workshop.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/pact-coffee.jpg" alt="Pact Coffee" /></a></p>

<p>We would like to thank Pact Coffee for donating their venue for this event. And another huge thank you to Hire Space for their generous donation towards this event.</p>

<p>Without the generous donations of both <a href="https://www.pactcoffee.com">Pact</a> and <a href="https://hirespace.com">Hire Space</a> this event would not have happened. If you are a company in South London and would like to sponsor an event, or donate your venue for the evening, then please get in contact at <a href="mailto:south-london@codebar.io">south-london@codebar.io</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Kickstart Your Development Career]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/03/26/kickstart-your-development-career/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-26T20:06:04+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/03/26/kickstart-your-development-career</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On the 16th of March a small group of aspiring developers came together at the <a href="https://gocardless.com/">GoCardless</a> offices in London for an evening event on how to <a href="http://codebar.io/courses/kickstart-your-developer-career">Kickstart Your Development Career</a>. The workshop, run by <a href="https://twitter.com/alinajaf">Najaf Ali</a>, was a three hour long presentation filled with practical knowledge and helpful tips on how to get your first job in web development.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/kickstart-your-dev-career.jpg" alt="Kickstart your dev career" /></a></p>

<p>The workshop consisted of three 30 minute sessions, each elaborating on a critical part of starting a career in web development.</p>

<p>In part one, Ali explained how to build tech skills and what to learn as an aspiring developer. The main takeaway from this section was to focus on one specific language (be it Ruby or Python or Javascript) or web development topic. Learning through printed books is still one of the best ways to gain strong knowledge of a language. Another key learning point was not to be put off by the less visually welcoming stuff: it is important to learn how to use the command line, to understand how Git works, and to get familiar with concepts like control structures, algorithms and relational databases such as MySQL. These skills will become increasingly important later on in your career. As a way of measuring skills, Ali suggested building lots of small projects, quantity over quality being key. Seeing what you can build from scratch without checking the internet for reference is also a good way to understand how much you actually know.</p>

<p>In part two Ali gave us tips on how to build influence and create a network in the tech industry. Going to meet ups and conferences is an excellent way to meet new people. Even better is talking at these events as these appearances can position you as an expert on a certain topic. Another way to build influence is to write a blog. Don&rsquo;t be afraid of coming off as an amateur - even the most basic piece of information can be useful to someone just getting into development. Another important point from this section was to have a couple of your best projects - around 2 to 3 - online and in a state where you can show them off to prospective employers at a moment&rsquo;s notice. And finally, on your personal website clearly state that you are available for work if that is the case.</p>

<p>Part three was concerned with the actual process of getting a job. Once again, we received a lot of useful tips from how to find job openings (it&rsquo;s always best if they come to you) to what to put on your CV. The most important lesson from this section was to have a plan: know what type of company you want to work for and target them specifically. Be confident in your skills and in your worth. Finally, be interested in the company and job you are applying for - genuine enthusiasm for the position and the company goes a long way.</p>

<p>All in all it was a very informative and helpful evening for the newbie programmers in attendance. If you are an aspiring developer keen on getting your first job in the industry or if you are one of the attendees and want to revisit the content of the workshop you can get the <a href="http://www.happybearsoftware.com/kickstart-your-developer-career">Kickstart Your Developer Career</a> book by signing up to <a href="http://www.happybearsoftware.com/kickstart-your-developer-career">this</a> mailing list.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bath Ruby Conference 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/03/22/bath-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T22:18:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/03/22/bath-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you happened to be in Bath last Friday, 13th of March, you would have seen a host of Ruby developers from the UK and beyond descend upon the ancient city for the first ever <a href="http://2015.bathruby.org/">Bath Ruby Conference</a> held at the Assembly Halls (chandeliers and all!). Such a fantastic event could not be missed, so went along for a full day of talks, learning and socialising.</p>

<p><a href="http://2015.bathruby.org/index.html"><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/bath-ruby-logo.png" alt="Bath Ruby Conference 2015" /></a></p>

<p><a href=""><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/bathruby-intro.jpg" alt="codebar organisers at Bath Ruby" /></a></p>

<p>Let me tell you, we had an amazing time! We met some of our coding heroes, most notably Sandi Metz, Katrina Owens, Ben Orenstein and Saron Yitbarek (yes, she is equally as nice in real life as she is on the <a href="http://www.codenewbie.org/">CodeNewbies</a> podcasts). We talked to amazing developers (both novice and more experienced), listened to some truly inspiring talks and had the opportunity to introduce <a href="http://codebar.io/">Codebar</a> on stage to the 500 strong crowd. We enjoyed an all together lovely, thought provoking day in the beautiful city of Bath.</p>

<p>No conference would be what it is without and excellent lineup of speakers (commendably 4/6 speakers were female) and topics, some of the highlights for us included:</p>

<p>Saron Yitbarek (<a href="https://twitter.com/saronyitbarek">@saronyitbarek</a>) spoke about the importance of supporting each other as you learn to code and develop as a novice programmer, because for those who don&rsquo;t get started at university or a bootcamp, it can be difficult to stay motivated when learning independently. In addition, she emphasized the importance of reading codebases written by other people &ndash; whether or not that code is &ldquo;good&rdquo; code &ndash; as one of the fastest ways to grow as a developer.</p>

<p>Katrina Owen (<a href="https://twitter.com/kytrinyx">@kytrinx</a>), the founder of <a href="http://www.exercism.io">exercism.io</a>, gave a talk on legacy code and the choices developers face on a daily basis: whether what you are contributing is actually moving the project forward or holding it back. She offered an explanation using Game Theory as to why developers (even good developers) will occasionally write bad code, which was extremely interesting, and perhaps a little bit too true for any developer in the audience who had worked with legacy code!</p>

<p>Tom Stuart&rsquo;s (<a href="https://twitter.com/tomstuart">@tomstuart</a>) talk wove many disparate concepts together into a talk about mathematical abstraction in software development. Using disarmingly simple slides, he explained how a concept as seemingly straightforward as bartering apples and bananas can be abstracted and applied to writing complex pieces of code. However, he emphasized that not all abstraction is good &ndash; abstraction is an effective means to an end when it is honest and minimal.</p>

<p>And finally Sandi Metz&rsquo;s (<a href="https://twitter.com/sandimetz">@sandimetz</a>) talk on nothing, and how sometimes nothing IS something. Her presentation featured an enormous diversity of Ruby topics, from metaprogramming to polymorphism to slightly off beat concepts like monkey-patching the Nil class. Although geared towards more advanced programmers, she ensured that new programmers in the room could access her insights on object-oriented Ruby.</p>

<p>We would like to thank the Bath Ruby organisers for putting together such an excellent event and for letting us spread the Codebar word. They did an excellent job - creating a friendly, inclusive, diverse and inspiring event. We&rsquo;ll definitely be back next year for another round of amazing talks and general merriment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Trans*Code London]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/02/22/transcode-london/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-22T15:19:28+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/02/22/transcode-london</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We are happy to announce our support for the <a href="http://trans-code.org">Trans*Code hackday</a> that will take place in London in March.</p>

<p><a href="http://trans-code.org"><img src="http://blog.codebar.io//images/trans-code.jpg" alt="Trans*Code" /></a></p>

<p>Trans*Code is a beginner friendly hack event focused on bringing together trans, non-binary, allies, coders, designers and visionaries and drawing attention to transgender issues and opportunities.</p>

<p>The event will kick off with an install-fest and a networking social on Friday, the 27th of March, followed by the main workshop and hackday on Saturday the 28th.</p>

<blockquote><p>“As technology offers growing opportunities, being sure these opportunities are equally accessible to traditionally marginalised groups grows ever more important. Participants can come from any background, working together to create prototypes around the themes of transgender issues and access to technology.” - Naomi Ceder, organiser</p></blockquote>

<p>If you have an idea, can code or design, want to learn, or just improve the situation of the trans and non­binary communities through technology <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/transcode-tickets-15831761224">sign up as a participant or volunteer to mentor</a>.</p>

<p>To keep up-to-date with Trans*Code events, follow <a href="http://twitter.com/trans_code">@trans_code</a> on twitter and subscribe to the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/trans_code?src=hash">event hashtag</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
