<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: conference | codebar]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//tags/conference/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//"/>
  <updated>2016-01-12T04:48:47+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.codebar.io//</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[codebar]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[EuRuKo 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/12/14/euruko-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-12-14T20:35:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/12/14/euruko-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Salzburg and the Sound of Music are traditionally inseparable, but there was little traditional about the sound of music in the Salzburg Congress hall in the middle of October.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="/images/salzburg.jpeg" alt="Salzburg" /></a></p>

<p>Joseph Wilk (<a href="https://twitter.com/josephwilk">@josephwilk</a>) was one of the presenters at <a href="http://www.euruko2015.org/">EuRuKo 2015</a>. He gave a talk and demo turning Ruby coding skills into a live performance.</p>

<p>What’s new and exciting about making music from code, Joseph said, is that it doesn’t matter that he’s making code. He’s simply making music.</p>

<p>Getting away from the traditionalist view of coding as something exclusive for certain types of programmers, is very exciting for him about coding today.</p>

<p>&ldquo;We’re reaching a point where people are starting to not accept how they’re told to use code. People are starting to say: let me discover for myself how I want to use it.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;And that brings wonderful new things together in new ways, like weaving and coding and design and coding. People are starting to break apart the technology and designing for themselves from scratch.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Some of these new things are what Dot, from <a href="https://codebar.io/brighton">codebar Brighton</a>, liked best about the conference.</p>

<p>&ldquo;You come to get an in-depth understanding of what’s involved in some aspects of the code.&rdquo; she said. &ldquo;But also to get different ideas. I’d never thought to make a game in Ruby.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;It was interesting to see Ruby in the GUI since we often tend to think of Ruby as a language that is only useful for writing web backends.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;When you’re writing Ruby in the day-to-day work environment there are many things you don’t think about, the conference shows you some of the fun things going on and some of the more obscure things.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Those obscure things included <a href="http://64bites.com/">64bites.com</a> founder Michał Taszycki (<a href="https://twitter.com/mehowte">@mehowte</a>) show the audience how to program a Commodore 64 and Amy Wibowo (<a href="https://twitter.com/sailorhg">@sailorhg</a>) demonstrate an exploration of origami’s cut and fold problem.</p>

<p>People of all ages and from countries all over the world came together under the umbrella of a common language in Ruby.</p>

<p>A language that allows people to think up an idea, work out how things need to be, and then make it into a working prototype or even program.</p>

<p>Dot, Foirell, Kriszta, Jen, and Sally from our codebar communities in London and Brighton went to the conference thanks to amazing London sponsor, <a href="https://shutl.com/uk/">@shutl</a>!</p>

<p>The keynote speaker was none other than Yukihiro &lsquo;Matz&rsquo; Matsumoto, the chief designer and mastermind behind Ruby.</p>

<p>He kicked off the conference with a visionary look at the interesting new stuff that the Ruby Core team is planning to add to Ruby, told through the humour of a Japanese language lesson. To the attendees relief, he also promised compatibility with Ruby 2.0.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="/images/matz.jpeg" alt="Yukihiro Matsumoto" /></a></p>

<p>Some of the more scientific and challenging talks were less Ruby specific: Bradley Grzesiak (<a href="https://twitter.com/listrophy">@listrophy</a>) spoke about simplifying challenging software problems with rocket science, while Satoshi Tagomori addressed a data analytics service and its Ruby usage.</p>

<p>Some combined both. Hanneli Tavante (<a href="https://twitter.com/hannelita">@hannelita</a>) spoke on Humanising Math and Physics on Computer Science. She said Ruby was her first language of choice because,</p>

<p>&ldquo;We see Ruby for DevOps such as automated scripts, or a simple parser, but it can fit most scenarios, and it&rsquo;s usage depends on what kind of performance you need and requirements.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;It’s easy for me to think in Ruby, but I think in Ruby and then if I need to for example, translate into Python. The syntax I find really pleasant too.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The language itself is very easy to write and it has some very interesting features. Ruby is good for beginners, and for senior developers.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;What’s new and exciting is also the development of the language towards new languages we have, such as Elixir, or Rust.&rdquo;</p>

<p>A more fun and personal highlight was the demo by Amy Wibowo – Fold, paper, scissors – an exploration of origami’s cut and fold problem.</p>

<p>The fold and cut theorem states that it is possible, given a piece of paper and any polygonal shape, to find a series of folds of that paper such that the given shape can be generated with a single cut.</p>

<p>Her talk explored a Ruby implementation of a solver that determined the correct series of folds given any input polygon.</p>

<p>What were some of the other take-aways?</p>

<p>René Föhring has created a tool called Inch, an inline documentation quality check, to get people excited about inline docs. <a href="http://shoesrb.com/">Shoes</a> for cross-platform GUI, <a href="http://sonic-pi.net/">Sonic Pi</a> for music composition, RbNaCl for cryptography.</p>

<p>In addition to the learnings, the Ruby community clearly also had a great time together over two days, and at the spirited Saturday night after-party.</p>

<p>That spirit is one reason to join a conference but also to join a community or club all year round.</p>

<p>Lisa Passing, Tam Eastleigh and Sarah Regan formed the <a href="http://rubycorns.club/jekyll/">rubycorns</a> in Berlin in 2013, a project group for Ruby beginners to learn and work on an app together.</p>

<p><a href=""><img src="/images/rubycorns.jpeg" alt="rubycorns" /></a></p>

<p>&ldquo;One of the challenges of learning Ruby is keeping motivated, it’s hard to know how to do that as a beginner. The community is great. People are kind and welcoming and excited to teach me.&rdquo;</p>

<p>And if she was starting out, I asked Lisa. What would she start with?</p>

<p>&ldquo;Start with a project like an app that you love to use, and build a clone of it. For us it was creating a list of support groups. Then figure out what you want to do. Figuring that out might be for fun or it might be your way of earning a living.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Typically Ruby is not as popular as other languages. While there are Ruby jobs out there, there are many more PHP and Java jobs but to Kevin McPhillips, Developer Team Lead at <a href="https://www.shopify.co.uk/">shopify</a>, the language you use is less important than being excellent.</p>

<p>The event&rsquo;s key sponsor told the audience that the market is massive and that attendees had, for example, probably used a Shopify store but not seen it behind the scenes:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Our core application is written on Ruby on Rails but we have a huge technology stack. Java, Python for the data science team, Go for some of our more concurrent tools.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;The company is hiring. We’re looking for people not specialists. I can teach someone a tool, we can teach excellent people anything.&rdquo;</p>

<p>Be excellent. As coders, as communicators, and as a community, that was a theme that hit all the right notes. Perhaps the best take away of all.</p>

<p>Check out the speakers’ decks here: <a href="http://eventifier.com/event/euruko2015/slides">http://eventifier.com/event/euruko2015/slides</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Responsive Day Out 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/06/26/responsive-day-out-3/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-26T10:23:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/06/26/responsive-day-out-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Friday 19th June was a brilliant day, partly because of the glorious sunshine and partly because 12 codebar Brighton students spent the day at the 3rd and final Responsive Day Out ‘The Final Breakpoint’ thanks to ticket giveaways from the lovely people at <a href="http://clearleft.com/">Clearleft</a>.</p>

<p><strong>What is Responsive Day Out?</strong></p>

<p>Responsive Day Out is a day conference comprised of topics branching responsive web design. It gathers designers and developers sharing their workflow strategies, techniques, and experiences with responsive web design.</p>

<p><strong>What is Responsive Web Design?</strong></p>

<p>Responsive web design is the practice of building a website suitable to work on every device and every screen size, no matter how large or small, mobile or desktop.</p>

<p>Building responsive websites primarily requires the use of HTML, CSS and possibly Javascript skills. This resonated well with the codebar students that attended as they have been building on these skills at codebar. The codebar tutorials don’t yet progress onto building responsive sites so this really got everyone thinking about how they could extend their current skill sets to encompass these ideas. It was also a real eye opener in to just how much there is to think about when designing for cross browser and cross platform.</p>

<p><strong>The Day!</strong></p>

<p>The conference was held at the Brighton Dome Corn Exchange, anyone who has been to Brighton will know that this is a beautiful building, well located between lots of nice places to eat and drink. The staff were friendly and helpful and the breaks made for a great opportunity to get to know some of the other attendees.</p>

<p>There were 12 talks, all of which were engaging and of high quality. Talks were grouped in 3s (around 20 minutes each) followed by a quick chat between conference host Jeremy Keith and those speakers before breaks for sun and coffee.</p>

<p><img src="/images/codebar_rdo.jpg" alt="codebar group photo" /></p>

<p><strong>The Speakers</strong></p>

<p>As codebar is an event aimed at encouraging diversity in tech we were pleased that there were so many inspiring female speakers on the bill. To us it signifies women holding strong presence in this industry. It is encouraging for other women either starting out or further into careers, when it is actively projected that women should be present, seen, heard and their knowledge shared.</p>

<p>The audio recordings are already available on the <a href="http://responsiveconf.com/2015/">Responsive Day Out 3 Page</a> but here is a quick overview of a few of the talks:</p>

<p><strong>Alice Bartlett -</strong></p>

<p>Alice is a front end developer at GDS and her talk title was ‘What is the business case of accessibility?’ She opened the conference, creating a great atmosphere as her speaking style came across very confident and naturally funny. She spoke about the alpha and beta stages of the GDS site and the process of making the site accessible. Ideas were developed with an objective: Not to frame what people may lack but instead to design in terms of what they (GDS) should provide. Through her experiences and through writing this talk, Alice found that accessibility is not the easiest businesses case to make but morally we should never need a business case for it. She recommended quick ways to improve accessibility to a site are running a screen reader over it and adding Aria. She also recommended joining discussions on the GDS <a href="https://designpatterns.hackpad.com/">Hack Pad</a> where design ideas are shared.</p>

<p><strong>Rachel Shillcock -</strong></p>

<p>Rachel is self employed, often designing for entrepreneurs with a focus on female entrepreneurs. She spoke about accessibility and how it isn’t something that can be tagged on at the end - no body should be left behind. She shared useful tools for making a site more accessible which will be especially useful for codebar students looking to make improvements in that area. These tools included <a href="http://leaverou.github.io/contrast-ratio/">Contrast Ratio</a> an online colour contrast checker that gives an A, AA or AAA accessibility rating for a colour against a background colour. Another was <a href="http://khan.github.io/tota11y/">tota11y</a> which lets you add a checklist to your page which will rate and advise your pages’ accessibility. Plenty of advice can also be found on <a href="http://a11yproject.com/">a11yproject</a>. She concluded that ultimately testing on real life people will help you achieve the best results.</p>

<p><strong>Alla Kholmatova -</strong></p>

<p>Alla is an interaction designer at FutureLearn. She spoke about taking a modular approach to design. She had found that a lack of shared language had hindered the original design process. They focused on perfecting the language used when naming components. A key takeaway was about how it was much harder to design ‘a kit’ than it was to design a whole page but the results were worthwhile. Another interesting part of their design process was that they actually handed away control from solely the designers and involved team members across disciplines. When working with users they worked with paper cards displaying the components which gave a more tangible and creative experience.</p>

<p><strong>Jake Archibald -</strong></p>

<p>Jake spoke about Modern Progressive Enhancement. Jake began by talking about performance and how the part to focus on is the time between the 1st render and 1st interaction. He spoke about the frustration of ‘lie-fi’ aka when your phone is telling you that you are connected but in reality the page never loads. He introduced the <a href="http://www.html5rocks.com/en/tutorials/service-worker/introduction/">Service Worker API</a> and how this will open up possibilities to browse offline. He demonstrated an app that allowed the user to make Wikipedia pages available offline. The problem then occurred if the user wanted to click on a link from the offline page and were not connected. In this instance, Service Worker could ask if the user would like to be notified when the page is available to view and could then send a push notification when the user next become connected. This seems like it would be very useful… especially for train journeys.</p>

<p><strong>Ruth John -</strong></p>

<p>Ruth’s talk was brilliant as she had prepared lots of demonstrations for using different web APIs. These included the geolocations API, web animation API, web audio API, ambient light API and more. There is a Web Audio API book by Boris Smus available to read for free online which comes recommended. Hopefully this triggered a few project ideas for codebar students!</p>

<p><strong>Rosie Campbell -</strong></p>

<p>Rosie works as a Technologist at BBC Research and Development which we thought seemed like a very cool job to have. She spoke about a research project they had undertaken with smart electronic wallpaper. The idea is that this wallpaper covers the walls in your living room and then when you watch tv the wall paper can change to give more of an immersive viewing experience spilling beyond the boundaries of the TV. You could be watching Glastonbury and there could be festival maps or set times or maybe a ‘Blur’ wall if Blur were playing with artwork from the band, possibly a crowd wall too. If there was a build up to a TV show you liked, maybe the photo frames could be slowly filled with character images over the course of the build up. This seems would also be great for parties if music videos could be projected all around the room.</p>

<p>Rosie spoke about designing with constraints to breed creativity which is why they kept a TV in the design. We recommend you read more about the Unconventional Screens project <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/rd/projects/unconventional-screens">here.</a></p>

<p><strong>Lyza Danger Gardner -</strong></p>

<p>Lyza was great to watch, very engaging and brilliant at telling the her story. She spoke about the conflicts she felt around being a generalist and working as a software engineer.  When she discovered HTML in 1993 she felt huge excitement - that she could reach the world with some p tags on a page. She loved pursuits with tangible results and felt the web was a generalist paradise. The web took a big leap when CSS was introduced and over time she began to find the complexity of the web tiring.</p>

<p>Before the web, if you heard lyrics on the radio you couldn’t just google the song. You had to look up academic information in reference libraries, but now with the web we are the reference library. More and more new frameworks are released and it can lead to demotivation and feelings of incomplete mastery making it much harder to be a generalist.</p>

<p>Lyza mentioned that she loved the word ‘developer’ which is something that resonated with some of the codebar students, it is great to be able to develop and carry out ideas. She spoke about how it takes bravery to feel like a beginner again and again as changes happen in the web. It is comforting to know that everyone feels out of their depth at times when learning.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>Responsive Day Out was a fabulous experience and we are slightly sad that this was the last one! Thank you very much to Clearleft and all the speakers. We came a way with a lot to think about and plenty of ideas to incorporate into our own projects.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bath Ruby Conference 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.codebar.io//2015/03/22/bath-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T22:18:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.codebar.io//2015/03/22/bath-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you happened to be in Bath last Friday, 13th of March, you would have seen a host of Ruby developers from the UK and beyond descend upon the ancient city for the first ever <a href="http://2015.bathruby.org/">Bath Ruby Conference</a> held at the Assembly Halls (chandeliers and all!). Such a fantastic event could not be missed, so went along for a full day of talks, learning and socialising.</p>

<p><a href="http://2015.bathruby.org/index.html"><img src="/images/bath-ruby-logo.png" alt="Bath Ruby Conference 2015" /></a></p>

<p><a href=""><img src="/images/bathruby-intro.jpg" alt="codebar organisers at Bath Ruby" /></a></p>

<p>Let me tell you, we had an amazing time! We met some of our coding heroes, most notably Sandi Metz, Katrina Owens, Ben Orenstein and Saron Yitbarek (yes, she is equally as nice in real life as she is on the <a href="http://www.codenewbie.org/">CodeNewbies</a> podcasts). We talked to amazing developers (both novice and more experienced), listened to some truly inspiring talks and had the opportunity to introduce <a href="http://codebar.io/">Codebar</a> on stage to the 500 strong crowd. We enjoyed an all together lovely, thought provoking day in the beautiful city of Bath.</p>

<p>No conference would be what it is without and excellent lineup of speakers (commendably 4/6 speakers were female) and topics, some of the highlights for us included:</p>

<p>Saron Yitbarek (<a href="https://twitter.com/saronyitbarek">@saronyitbarek</a>) spoke about the importance of supporting each other as you learn to code and develop as a novice programmer, because for those who don&rsquo;t get started at university or a bootcamp, it can be difficult to stay motivated when learning independently. In addition, she emphasized the importance of reading codebases written by other people &ndash; whether or not that code is &ldquo;good&rdquo; code &ndash; as one of the fastest ways to grow as a developer.</p>

<p>Katrina Owen (<a href="https://twitter.com/kytrinyx">@kytrinx</a>), the founder of <a href="http://www.exercism.io">exercism.io</a>, gave a talk on legacy code and the choices developers face on a daily basis: whether what you are contributing is actually moving the project forward or holding it back. She offered an explanation using Game Theory as to why developers (even good developers) will occasionally write bad code, which was extremely interesting, and perhaps a little bit too true for any developer in the audience who had worked with legacy code!</p>

<p>Tom Stuart&rsquo;s (<a href="https://twitter.com/tomstuart">@tomstuart</a>) talk wove many disparate concepts together into a talk about mathematical abstraction in software development. Using disarmingly simple slides, he explained how a concept as seemingly straightforward as bartering apples and bananas can be abstracted and applied to writing complex pieces of code. However, he emphasized that not all abstraction is good &ndash; abstraction is an effective means to an end when it is honest and minimal.</p>

<p>And finally Sandi Metz&rsquo;s (<a href="https://twitter.com/sandimetz">@sandimetz</a>) talk on nothing, and how sometimes nothing IS something. Her presentation featured an enormous diversity of Ruby topics, from metaprogramming to polymorphism to slightly off beat concepts like monkey-patching the Nil class. Although geared towards more advanced programmers, she ensured that new programmers in the room could access her insights on object-oriented Ruby.</p>

<p>We would like to thank the Bath Ruby organisers for putting together such an excellent event and for letting us spread the Codebar word. They did an excellent job - creating a friendly, inclusive, diverse and inspiring event. We&rsquo;ll definitely be back next year for another round of amazing talks and general merriment.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
